<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen at the Guild-Hall Chappel, Jan. 20, 1683 by John Standish ...</title>
            <author>Standish, John, d. 1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61268</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13597</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13587055</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13587055</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100576</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61268)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100576)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 851:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen at the Guild-Hall Chappel, Jan. 20, 1683 by John Standish ...</title>
                  <author>Standish, John, d. 1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Hills, Jun., for Robert Calvell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published at the desire of the Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Deuteronomy VI, 11-12 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100576:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the RIGHT HONOURABLE THE Lord Mayor, AND Court of ALDERMEN, AT THE <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ILD-HALL</hi> CHAPPEL, <hi>Jan.</hi> 20. 1683.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Standiſh,</hi> D.D. Rector of <hi>Therfield,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to HIS MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed at the Deſire of the LORD MAYOR and Court of ALDERMEN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. Hills,</hi> Jun. for <hi>Robert Clavell,</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100576:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100576:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable Sir, HENRY TULSE, Lord Mayor, And to the Court of ALDERMEN.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT was ſomewhat <hi>late</hi> before I received your <hi>Commands,</hi> (for <hi>ſuch</hi> I ever ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the <hi>Deſires</hi> of my Lawful <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours</hi>) which is one reaſon that this <hi>ſhort Diſcourſe</hi> hath been ſo <hi>long</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your Hands.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100576:3"/>
            <p>And I ſhall not trouble your Lordſhip with any other Apology, becauſe it was not framed for, nor fixed to any <hi>Solemn</hi> Time, or <hi>Special</hi> Occaſion, but with an equal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to every <hi>Day</hi> in the <hi>Year,</hi> or rather to all the <hi>Days</hi> of our <hi>Lives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed, the <hi>Subject</hi> thereof is <hi>Common,</hi> but not therefore to be deſpiſed, more then any other <hi>Common Good:</hi> more then our <hi>Common Prayers, Common Salvation,</hi> or our <hi>Common Faith,</hi> which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle elſewhere calls our <hi>Precious Faith,</hi> (or <hi>Honourable,</hi> as the Greek imports.) And the more <hi>Common</hi> things of Publick uſe and conſequence are, they ſhould be ſo much the more <hi>Precious</hi> in our Eyes.</p>
            <p>'Tis true the <hi>Scene</hi> is laid in <hi>LONDON,</hi> yet not ſo confined thither, but it may reach the remoteſt parts of the <hi>Nation;</hi> for this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Mapp preſents you with a Tranſient view of the <hi>preſent State,</hi> and Morals of all <hi>ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>England!</hi> another <hi>Canaan,</hi> for Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Wealth, Proſperity, Peace, and Plenty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all good things that a Loyal <hi>Heart can wiſh</hi> and yet, (I wiſh I could not truly ſay) another <hi>Canaan</hi> too, for <hi>Ingratitude,</hi> and <hi>forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> GOD their Saviour. The happieſt <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:100576:3"/>under Heaven at this hour, and only <hi>miſerable</hi> in this, that we do not know how <hi>Happy</hi> we are. For we may fairly challenge all <hi>Europe</hi> for a more Gracious KING, a more Glorious CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH, a more Peaceable STATE, a more Gentle and Eaſie GOVERN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT, more Juſt and Wholeſome LAWS, and yet we cannot, way, we <hi>will not</hi> ſee it. We are unthankful ſtill, and ſtill murmuring, and know not what we would have, unleſs we would be <hi>Angels</hi> before the time.</p>
            <p>This provoking ill Humour hath of late ſpread it ſelf throughout the Kingdom; and therefore my Arguments againſt it are ſo <hi>General,</hi> and take in all ſorts and degrees of Men, all that would be thought good <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> or good <hi>Subjects;</hi> the very <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> themſelves are not a little concerned therein, if they pleaſe to read them without that falſe Glaſs of guilty <hi>Prejudice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However <hi>they</hi> deal with us for doing our Daty, and <hi>ſpeaking the Truth in Love,</hi> ſo long as we have Patronage and Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from your Lordſhips <hi>Chair,</hi> and that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Bench,</hi> we ſhall never think our <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi> loſt, or unrewarded.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100576:4"/>
            <p>The <hi>time</hi> hath been, when <hi>Men</hi> in Your Lordſhips High Place, <hi>would not endure ſound Doctrine, having itching Ears.</hi> Thanks be to GOD and his <hi>Vicegerent,</hi> that <hi>time</hi> is now paſt, and the Caſe ſo well alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that <hi>ſound Doctrine,</hi> and ſincere <hi>Loyalty</hi> will as eaſily go down, and paſs muſter in the <hi>City,</hi> as at <hi>Court.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With my hearty <hi>Prayers</hi> for the long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of GODS Bleſſing upon Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, your <hi>Loyal Brethren,</hi> and the whole Government of this City, I am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Obedient Servant, <hi>John Standiſh.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100576:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deut. VI. part of the 11, and 12</hi> verſes.</bibl>
               <q>—When thou ſhalt have Eaten, and be Full, then beware leſt thou forget the LORD.—</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>PRoſperity and Adverſity are the great Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres of Humane life; the two famous Teſts to prove what <hi>Spirit</hi> and temper Men <hi>are of,</hi> for it is an Error of the <hi>Vulgar</hi> only, that all is well, when their Gold and Silver, Flocks and Herds, Corn and Wine <hi>increaſe</hi> and grow upon them; <hi>Wiſer</hi> Men find it as hard a task, (at leaſt) to command and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage a head-ſtrong, flowing fortune, as to keep them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from ſinking, and being deſperate, when they are reduced to their loweſt Ebb, laſt Shifts, and Wits end. It is an old Queſtion amongſt the learned Moraliſts, which of the two Eſtates is moſt entangled with dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and difficulties? the great cry is out upon <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity,</hi> who by her killing Smiles, treacherous En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments, and ſtealing Flatteries, Effeminates, and Robbs the Spirit of its due force and vigour; She baſely betrays the Fort by letting the Enemy in at a Poſtern, and eaſily conquers thoſe daring Heroes who never turned their backs of viſible danger: Whom no <hi>Adverſe</hi> affair, not <hi>Death</hi> it ſelf, in all its frigthful change of ſhapes, could ever daunt, or daſh out of Countenance.</p>
            <p>And indeed 'tis a <hi>Truth</hi> which the Oracles of GOD have vouched to us by no mean Inſtances to put it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all diſpute. For whileſt <hi>Gideon</hi> was a private
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100576:5"/>man, <hi>the leaſt in his Fathers houſe,</hi> and <hi>threſhed Wheat by the Wine-preſs,</hi> he was a very Good man, and a great Favourite in the Court of Heaven; the Text ſays, that the <hi>Angel of the LORD viſited</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muned</hi> freely <hi>with him,</hi> as a Man does with his <hi>Friend;</hi> but then, when once He grew <hi>Great,</hi> and was fleſhed with a miraculous victory over the <hi>mighty Kings of Midian,</hi> the ſame man was not the <hi>ſame;</hi> for he abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his proſperous fortune, and made him an <hi>Ephod of the Ear-rings taken</hi> in <hi>ſpoil,</hi> and <hi>put it in His City</hi> Ophrah, <hi>and all Iſrael went a whoring after it, which thing became a ſnare to</hi> Gideon <hi>and his houſe.</hi> Thus one bewitching <hi>Dalilah</hi> ſubdued the invincible <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> when all other Arts and Arms of <hi>Paleſtine</hi> could neither withſtand, no, nor <hi>find out his ſtrength. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was troubled I went wrong,</hi> ſaith King <hi>David:</hi> And — <hi>It is good for me that I was afflicted;</hi> that ſet him <hi>right.</hi> But then again when He ſat ſtill at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in a profound Peace, and had nothing elſe to do, He fell into thoſe two grievous Sins which cut him out work for <hi>Repentance</hi> all the days of his Life. His ſon <hi>Solomon,</hi> the <hi>wiſeſt</hi> Prince that ever ſwayed That, or any other Scepter under the Sun, yet ſtands charged with very great <hi>folly</hi> towards the end of his peaceable Reign; for living in all eaſe and pleaſure, and having no manner of <hi>Enemies,</hi> but thoſe moſt deadly ones of his <hi>own houſe,</hi> his Falſe Friends, he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adviſedly ſuffer'd them in <hi>his Old</hi> declining <hi>Age</hi> to tempt him to <hi>Idolatry.</hi> To add no more, <hi>Iſrael</hi> in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral who found the land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> that <hi>houſe</hi> of <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage</hi> and hardſhip, a wholeſome School of <hi>Vertue,</hi> made the bleſſed Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> a Nourſe of all <hi>Vices,</hi> a mere <hi>Land of forgetfulneſs;</hi> which <hi>Moſes</hi> the <hi>Man</hi> of GOD here having a clear proſpect of, he lays in early caution againſt it in theſe words, — <hi>When thou
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100576:5"/>ſhalt have eaten, and be full, then beware leſt thou forget the LORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For our due handling of theſe words I ſhall endeavour,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To ſtate the genuine ſenſe and full importance of the <hi>caution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To back and enforce it with ſome proper Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And Laſtly, To tender ſome ſhort directive Rules how we may beſt reduce it to Practice.</p>
            <p>I begin with the Firſt; And</p>
            <p n="1">1. To <hi>forget the</hi> LORD, imports in general, to contemn the power of <hi>Religion,</hi> and with that old <hi>Fool,</hi> to <hi>ſay in ones heart, there is no GOD,</hi> no Judge, or Judgment to come; at leaſt to deny Him that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Worſhip due to His <hi>Holy and Reverend Name,</hi> and give it to Another; to put ones truſt and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in <hi>Creatures</hi> or <hi>Idols,</hi> the works of God's, or of Mens hands, more then the <hi>Creator,</hi> and caſt his Commandments <hi>behind ones back,</hi> as if he owed no duty either to God or Man: It implies a ſtupid ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitual neglect of <hi>Gods Service,</hi> which is the great bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, and chief end of our Creation; when a Man immerſeth himſelf ſo deep in the fruitleſs cares, the frothy Vanities of this World, and the ſinful Luſts of the Fleſh, that GOD <hi>is not in all his</hi> ferious <hi>thoughts,</hi> that is, not in <hi>one</hi> of them <hi>All;</hi> but he lives and dies an Atheiſt, Epicure, Idolater, or ungodly Infidel, and ſo plungeth himſelf, headlong into that dreadful Doom in the Pſalm, <hi>The wicked ſhall be turned into Hell, and all the Nations that forget</hi> GOD.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To <hi>forget</hi> the LORD ſignifies here more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, not to recount and value, not to be duly <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible</hi> of, and truly <hi>thankful</hi> for his paſt or preſent <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> and <hi>Deliverances;</hi> not to lay them to <hi>heart,</hi> and call them to <hi>mind:</hi> not to ſuffer them to have their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100576:6"/>proper effect upon us, when his <hi>own</hi> beloved and of late diſtreſſed <hi>People</hi> forget GOD their SAVIOUR, who brought them out of <hi>Aegypt</hi> with a high <hi>Hand,</hi> and ſtretched out Arm; who <hi>led them through the Wilderneſs,</hi> and fought all their <hi>battels</hi> for them, drowning ſome of their Enemies in the depth of the <hi>Sea,</hi> and routing all others at <hi>Land,</hi> and planted them in a good Land, in another <hi>Paradice;</hi> even the <hi>Land of Promiſe;</hi> a Land of <hi>Corn, Wine, and Oyl,</hi> a Land <hi>flowing</hi> with Rivers of <hi>Milk</hi> and Brooks of <hi>Honey.</hi> For them to Rebel and lift up their heel againſt Him merely out of <hi>wantonneſs,</hi> and too much <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Plenty,</hi> were beyond all <hi>Parallel,</hi> if not all <hi>Pardon</hi> alſo; for, as the Royal Prophet obſerves, <hi>the merciful and gracious</hi> LORD, <hi>hath ſo done his marvellous works, that they ought to be had in Remembrance.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</p>
            <p n="3">3. And Laſtly, To diſcover the full ſtrength and force of the <hi>Caution,</hi> we muſt fly to that uſual figure in <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> whereby much more is <hi>implied</hi> then is <hi>expreſſed,</hi> like that of the Prophet, <hi>Can a Woman for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get her ſucking Child, and not have compaſſion on the Son of her Womb?</hi> It is impoſſible in Nature: That of St. <hi>Paul, I am not aſhamed of,</hi> that is, I glory in the <hi>Goſpel</hi> and <hi>Croſs</hi> of CHRIST, albeit the <hi>wiſe</hi> Greeks account it <hi>Fooliſhneſs;</hi> or that of the holy Pſalmiſt;—<hi>If I forget thee ô</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>let my right hand for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get her cunning; if I do not remember thee, then let my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth;</hi> the ſweet ſinger of <hi>Iſrael</hi> wiſheth his curious <hi>right hand</hi> uſeleſs, and his graceful <hi>Tongue</hi> diſabled from chanting any more <hi>Hallelujahs</hi> to his <hi>Harp,</hi> if (inſtead of forgetting) He doth not prefer <hi>Jeruſalem's</hi> diſtreſs above his own chiefeſt Delight and Joy. <hi>Then beware leſt thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the</hi> LORD: That is, be ſure that thou <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:100576:6"/>to love and honour him in the day of thy <hi>Proſperity</hi> for <hi>then</hi> thou haſt all the reaſon in the world, and the; ſtrongeſt obligations imaginable, to praiſe and glorifie his <hi>holy Name,</hi> and that <hi>not in Word and Tongue only,</hi> ſaying GOD be thanked, the LORD be praiſed; (though that ſounds well) but <hi>indeed and in Truth alſo,</hi> as that dying <hi>Roman</hi> ſaid to his <hi>Friend, Quae voluerit meminiſſe, quae mandaverit exequi.</hi> —To <hi>remember</hi> his Will and Pleaſure, and <hi>do</hi> all his Commands. For to be truly <hi>thankful</hi> to GOD is certainly to <hi>love</hi> him: and <hi>if ye love me, keep my Commandments,</hi> ſaith the LORD.</p>
            <p>And yet after all, that <hi>Jeſhurun waxing fat</hi> in her freſh Paſture, grew ſturdy and reſtiff, and <hi>Kick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt her Feeder,</hi> and moſt ſhamefully forgot the Lord her Redemer, appears by the Writings of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> as a <hi>Cloud of Witneſſes,</hi> as alſo by thoſe ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious <hi>Showers of Judgments</hi> which fell upon them, according to the Predictions of thoſe <hi>Prophets;</hi> and laſtly by their utter Extirpation, and Deſtruction, their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Blotted out of the Liſt of <hi>Nations</hi> for <hi>Crucifying the Lord of Life,</hi> and Killing their only Lord and Saviour. For to this day they are under a Curſe, they are Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds over all the Earth, they are no People, they have no Laws or Government, no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God nor Man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which things happened unto them for Enſamples</hi> (ſays St. <hi>Paul</hi>) and <hi>are written,</hi> that is, left upon Record Chiefly, <hi>for our Admonition upon whom the Ends of the World are come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore leſt we ſhould tread in their Ungra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Steps, and <hi>forget the</hi> Lord when we are full fed with his Manifold Mercies; leſt we <hi>ſhould tempt Chriſt, as ſome of them alſo tempted, and be Deſtroyed of the Deſtroyer; leſt our Iniquity alſo ſhould be our Ruine;</hi> I proceed,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:100576:7"/>2ly. To back and Inforce this ſeaſonable <hi>Caution</hi> with ſome proper <hi>Arguments</hi> or <hi>Confiderations,</hi> that it may make the deeper Impreſſion upon all our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider we that by <hi>forgetting</hi> GOD and grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing careleſs of his Laws in the midſt of our temporal Felicities, we provoke the beſt <hi>Friend</hi> we have to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our profeſſed Enemy. For they draw not GODS Attributes to the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> who allow him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Mercy</hi> for a Penitent, and no <hi>Juſtice</hi> at all for a Preſumptuous Sinner. They are more Falſe Prophets then <hi>Balaam</hi> himſelf, who would ſtretch the Words of his <hi>Parable</hi> to ſignifie, that GOD <hi>doth not behold,</hi> but Connive at all manner of <hi>Iniquity</hi> in the beloved <hi>Jacob,</hi> becauſe he ſaw none there <hi>at that time,</hi> that cried loud enough for Speedy and Publick <hi>Vengeance,</hi> which is the undoubted meaning of that Place. No; GOD is not ſo fond of any of his Servants, as to be in love with their Follies: The deareſt Child he hath muſt taſt of the <hi>Rod</hi> if he deſerve it. <hi>David</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>a Man after GODS own heart</hi> in other things, but yet his <hi>Murder</hi> and <hi>Adultery</hi> were <hi>Damnable</hi> Sins for all that, as he had found by woful Experience, if he had not carefully waſhed them away with his own Penitent <hi>Tears,</hi> more Richly Influenced with his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemers <hi>Blood.</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> was a Man of Undaunted Courage, and moſt forward <hi>Faith</hi> at other times, but yet there is no excuſe to be made for his denying his Lord and Maſter, and that with an Oath, ſaying, <hi>I know not the Man. Iſrael</hi> was once GODS <hi>Elect peculiar People</hi> of all others, <hi>Engraven upon the Palms of his Hands,</hi> and <hi>kept as the Apple of his Eye,</hi> (ſo tender he was of them) but all this while their Sins <hi>were written with a Pen of Iron,</hi> and <hi>the point of a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, to ſhew that the Memory of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100576:7"/>them was laſting, and they ſo far from being winked at, that they were more ſurely and ſpeedily puniſhed, then if they had been <hi>Aliens.</hi> Witneſs the many <hi>Woes</hi> and <hi>Threats, Judgments</hi> and <hi>Curſes</hi> diſcharged upon them at divers times; ſuch as <hi>Peſtilence</hi> and <hi>Famine, Blaſting</hi> and <hi>Mildew,</hi> the <hi>Sword,</hi> the <hi>Fiery Serpents,</hi> the <hi>Heavens</hi> ſometimes as <hi>Iron,</hi> the <hi>Earth</hi> as <hi>Braſs. Becauſe my People hath forgotten me, I will ſcatter them as with an Eaſt-Wind before the Enemy; I will ſhew them the Back, and not the Face in the day of their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity,</hi> Jerem. 18. And again, <hi>I will be unto them as a Lyon, or a Leopard, as a Bear bereaved of her Whelps: I will Rent the Cawl of their hearts, and Devour them like a Lyon, ſaith the LORD,</hi> Hos. 13. All this to that <hi>Beloved People.</hi> So that however Vain Men may fancy, that their being of the Number of GODS <hi>Elect,</hi> and in a State of <hi>Grace,</hi> is a ſufficient Patent or Priviledge to excuſe their Sins, yet the Caſe is clear that they <hi>deceive</hi> themſelves herein, although they be (if 'twere poſſible) of the <hi>very Elect.</hi> For be he Jew or Chriſtian, be he Saint or Angel, that <hi>Forgets</hi> his GOD, he thereby Forfeits his Favour and Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Incurrs his utmoſt Enmity and Wrath; he loſeth the <hi>Light of his Countenance,</hi> and makes the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs</hi> appear to him in no other, then that Terrible ſhape of <hi>a Conſuming Fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Argument alone, methinks, ſhould be ſtrong enough to drive the Nail home; <hi>beware leſt thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the LORD,</hi> for thereby thou wilt make him thine <hi>Enemy;</hi> and a Potent <hi>Enemy</hi> he is, worthy of all thy fear: For he can Torment thee with a thouſand Plagues here, and then Caſt both Body and Soul into the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermoſt Hell</hi> hereafter.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider that to <hi>forget</hi> GOD when we are <hi>Daily Loaden</hi> with his <hi>Bleſſings,</hi> would argue us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100576:8"/>diſingenuous, and baſely <hi>Ingrateful,</hi> the moſt deteſtable Name of all others; call me that, and call me worſe if you can. A <hi>Name</hi> that Nature it ſelf ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors: For, not to mention the Stork (that Famous Symbol of Piety,) very Lyons and Wolves, Tygers, and Bears are Civil and Grateful to their own <hi>Parents</hi> and Relatives. Only the Noble and <hi>Rational</hi> Creature that calls himſelf <hi>Man,</hi> in this exceeds the very <hi>Beaſts that Periſh:</hi> That he is ſometimes Ingrateful to his own <hi>Kind,</hi> oftner to his <hi>King,</hi> but moſt of all to his moſt Gracious GOD. Inſomuch that the Almighty doth, as it were, Challenge the whole <hi>Creation</hi> to Match or Vie with his Unworthyneſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. <hi>Hear O, Heavens, and give ear O Earth! for the LORD hath ſpoken; I have nouriſhed and brought up Children, and they have Rebelled againſt me.</hi> The Complaint is of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſtill, the <hi>peculiar People,</hi> and may it be pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to them alone; <hi>but let it not be told in</hi> Gath, <hi>nor publiſhed in the Streets of</hi> Askelon, that we ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver deſerve that unnatural Brand and moſt odieus Name of <hi>Ingrateful</hi> Chriſtians.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertainty</hi> of our preſent happineſs and <hi>Halcyon</hi> Days of Peace and Plenty. For GOD lets no Leaſes for <hi>Lives</hi> in diſpenſing his Temporal Bleſſings: We are all but <hi>Tenants at will,</hi> and may be turn'd out of all, and Beggar'd at his Pleaſure. There is, ye know, a natural Viciſſitude of things: The whole World is ever turning Round, Day and Night, Summer and Winter have their mutual Courſes. The moſt Glorious Day is ſhut up with a pitchy Night, a dull, uncouth Winter uſually follows the moſt Spright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Summer; nay, the Sun is oft ſequeſter'd of his Noon day <hi>Glory</hi> by a <hi>little Cloud</hi> appearing firſt like a <hi>Mans hand,</hi> but afterwards ſhewing it ſelf to be more like the <hi>Hand</hi> of <hi>him</hi> who ſometimes <hi>makes Darkneſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100576:8"/>his Pavilion,</hi> though he ever <hi>dwells in in acceſſible Light.</hi> A very lively Emblem of the Inſtability of all humane affairs, which admit of as much <hi>change</hi> of Weather, as Nature it ſelf. For there is ſeldom one Sun-ſhine day of <hi>Peace,</hi> but a <hi>Cloud</hi> riſes in the midſt on't, from whence the Thunder and Lightning of Fatal <hi>Wars</hi> breaks out of a ſudden; however Night is drawing on, and will at length overtake us, and then all our Joys and Comforts will ſuffer a more continued Interrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, perhaps be totally Eclipſed by Trouble and Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>Nulla ſors longa &amp;, dolor eſt voluptas invicem ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt, brevior voluptas,</hi> ſays the excellent <hi>Tragedian;</hi> no condition of Life here, not the beſt is fixed and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable: Sorrow and Joy take their turns, (there go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing commonly a whole day of Trouble to one hour of Joy) and the <hi>Stars in their Courſes fight</hi> either for, or againſt us according as we demean our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Beloved, our Memories are treacherous indeed, if we have quite forgotten the ſevere Diſcipline GOD hath of late Years exerciſed upon this <hi>City,</hi> and this Sinful <hi>Nation,</hi> Chiefly by the devouring <hi>Sword,</hi> the Raging <hi>Peſtilence,</hi> and the Conſuming <hi>Fire;</hi> for all which we ought to <hi>lay</hi> our <hi>hands upon our Mouths,</hi> and acknowledg them as juſt <hi>Judgments</hi> upon us for our <hi>forgetting</hi> GOD in the midſt of our Jollity. Thoſe <hi>Storms</hi> (through Mercy) are at preſent over, and we in a very great <hi>Calm;</hi> we enjoy more Temporal Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licities (if we would ſee it) <hi>then even heart could wiſh,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks; though we hear of nothing but <hi>Wars, and Rumours of Wars abroad,</hi> yet we are not <hi>trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at home,</hi> (bating our own groundleſs Jealouſies, and Superſtitious Fears) farther then to <hi>ſit down</hi> quietly under our own <hi>Vines and Fig-trees,</hi> and Reap the Fruit of GODS Bleſſing upon our own Labours. GOD hath marveluoſly <hi>turned our</hi> great <hi>Captivity</hi> long ago,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100576:9"/>
               <hi>as the Rivers in the South:</hi> He hath ever ſince given us <hi>Beauty for Aſhes, The Oyl of Joy for Sorrow, and the Garment of Praiſe for the Spirit of Heavineſs.</hi> All the danger is, leſt we alſo grow ſick of <hi>Iſraels</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe: Leſt we become <hi>proud</hi> and <hi>preſumptuous,</hi> wax <hi>wanton,</hi> and careleſs of paying him due Returns, and ſo make our own <hi>Tables a Snare,</hi> our very <hi>Bleſſings</hi> a <hi>Curſe.</hi> GOD doth not intend to <hi>kill</hi> us with his <hi>Kindneſſes;</hi> but, if we know not when we are well; if we can't wield and manage a full and <hi>proſperous</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate; if nothing but a <hi>Furnace</hi> will melt us into Tears, and purge away our Droſs and Follies, (wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Duſt as we are!) into the <hi>Furnace</hi> we muſt go again even until <hi>ſeven times:</hi> The <hi>Scene</hi> will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alter in a Moment, the Wheel of things turn quite <hi>round,</hi> and the <hi>end of our ſorrows, be far worſe then the beginning.</hi> Then let not the Pride of thine Heart de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thee, O Man, and ſay not thou, who ſhall diſturb me when I am at <hi>reſt in my Poſſeſſions,</hi> or <hi>Tranſgreſſions;</hi> for <hi>though thou exalt thy ſelf</hi> as an <hi>Eagle, and ſet thy Neſt among the Stars, yet thence will I bring thee down ſaith the LORD</hi> Obad. v. 4.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider the many ſolemn <hi>Vows</hi> and <hi>Promiſes</hi> we offered up to GOD in our diſtreſs, to make our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for deliverance effectual and ſuccesful; for they will all be required at our hands, as ſo many further Obligations we freely laid upon our ſelves, not to <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get</hi> the LORD in the day of our Rejoycing.</p>
            <p>It is the Natural effect of <hi>Adverſity</hi> to make Men <hi>conſider,</hi> and grow <hi>Wiſer:</hi> To <hi>come to themſelves,</hi> to their right <hi>Wits,</hi> like the <hi>Prodigal</hi> reduced to his laſt <hi>husk.</hi> No Lectures of Morality make ſuch Impreſſion, as thoſe that are back'd with the Rod of <hi>Affliction;</hi> no <hi>Law</hi> compels and forces its own <hi>Execution,</hi> like that of <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> which makes us ſay proverbially, <hi>that hath no
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100576:9"/>Law againſt it.</hi> I remember <hi>Lactantius</hi> obſerves well that the very <hi>Pagans</hi> themſelves when Scourged with depopulating <hi>Wars,</hi> Contagious Diſeaſes, unuſual droughts, great Rains, Inundations, Storms, Hurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans, or any other grievous publick Calamity, fall down on their knees preſently to the GOD of Heaven, and invoke him earneſtly and unanimouſly, with <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> and <hi>Tears</hi> to divert and remove his <hi>Judgment</hi> from them. To which he adds, if any of them be reduced to extream Poverty, and forced to beg his <hi>Bread</hi> from Door to Door, he makes uſe of the Name of GOD, as the moſt powerful Argument of his <hi>Petition,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching Men for GODS ſake to have pitty and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on <hi>Him.</hi> But then (as he goes on) <hi>poſtquàm metus deſer uit</hi> &amp;c. So ſoon as ever they are well rid of that danger, Fear, or Miſery, they return in whole Shoals to the <hi>CON<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ENTICLES</hi> of their <hi>Idol Gods,</hi> and Sacrifice all the time of their Proſperity to <hi>them; Lact. Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Divin. Inſtit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe were profeſſed <hi>Heathen,</hi> but what ſhall we ſay, if ſome pretended <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are not aſhamed to Act the ſame part, or ſomething very like it.</p>
            <p>I might bring in the <hi>Merchant</hi> in a <hi>Storm,</hi> who will offer freely even to <hi>half,</hi> nay <hi>all</hi> his Eſtate to Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable uſes (rather then fail) provided he may have <hi>his Life for a prey: Skin for Skin</hi> will he venture for that; but when that danger is once over and he got ſafe a Shore, he forfeits his <hi>Vow,</hi> and cheats his GOD, by making ſome three-penny Largeſs or pitiful <hi>Alms</hi> to ſerve the turn.</p>
            <p>Or I might tell you at large of the Woman in <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail,</hi> who goes for a pure <hi>Saint,</hi> a Seraphick <hi>Votreſs,</hi> whilſt the pangs of <hi>Death</hi> are upon her, but ſoon after her more formal then hearty <hi>Acknowledgments,</hi> ſhe ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly <hi>forgets</hi> that great, though common <hi>Deliverance.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:100576:10"/>
            <p>But I ſhall only inſtance in the Man thrown into a <hi>Malignant Feaver</hi> by his own intemperance, when the Diſeaſe grows upon him, and begins to prey upon his <hi>Vitals,</hi> inſomuch that his ableſt Phyſicians <hi>halt between two opinions,</hi> whether he will Live, or Die, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf finds ſmall hopes of Recovery from within; Oh! what Sighs and Groans are fetcht from the very bottom of his <hi>Heart!</hi> what earneſt Prayers, what loud indefatigable Expoſtulations proceed out of his <hi>Mouth!</hi> what an importunate Suit doth he preſent before the <hi>Throne of Grace,</hi> that he may be <hi>ſpared</hi> a <hi>little, little while, and have ſpace to Repent before he go hence, and be no more ſeen!</hi> what Golden <hi>Promiſes</hi> doth he freely paſs, what warm Proteſtations doth he make of his ſpeedy <hi>Converſion!</hi> Oh that I could but eſcape this one approaching Fiery <hi>Fit!</hi> I would moſt certainly become a <hi>New Man;</hi> I would Correct the dangerous Errors of my <hi>Ways,</hi> Contemn the little Luſts and Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the World, and ſerve my GOD with all my <hi>Heart,</hi> with all my <hi>Soul,</hi> and all my <hi>Strength.</hi> Sweet JESUS grant me but this one Requeſt, try me once more; and if I be not henceforth a <hi>Reformed</hi> Man, I ask no more Mercy; then let me <hi>die the Death!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly the Man ſpeaks well, and who would not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that he is in <hi>Earneſt?</hi> conſidering they are (for ought he knows) the <hi>laſt</hi> words he is to ſay. Well! the Almighty hears, and is overcome by his importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: He reſtores his <hi>Health</hi> and Strength beyond all humane expectation, and renews the Leaſe of his <hi>Life</hi> for many, very many Years.—Now is it poſſible for this Man to be worſe then his word? I am afraid—No; I am aſhamed to tell you, but rather refer it to your own daily and ſad <hi>Experience.</hi> Yet thus much I muſt needs ſay, that if after all this, he Relapſe into his former wicked Life, he is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt,</hi> as well as <hi>Ingrateful</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:100576:10"/>to his GOD, and the <hi>laſt Eſtate of that Man muſt needs be far worſe then the firſt.</hi> Which that it may never be Verified of any of us, I befeech you let us call to mind the time paſt, and ſeriouſly reflect upon the Sacred <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions</hi> we took, and Solemn <hi>Promiſes</hi> we made to GOD in our extreme diſtreſs, and be careful with <hi>DAVID to pay all our Vows unto the moſt High.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Laſtly, Conſider we the true <hi>Reaſons</hi> that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved GOD to turn our <hi>Captivity,</hi> pluck down Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and Oppreſſors, and Redeem us from a more than <hi>Egyptian Bondage;</hi> to renew our former Peace and Happineſs, Reſtore our loſt <hi>Religion,</hi> and Ancient Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and give us <hi>Princes as at the firſt, and Judges as at the Beginning.</hi> For that <hi>Succeſs</hi> muſt needs infer a good <hi>Cauſe,</hi> is a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> fallacy, which yet of late, hath much impoſed upon the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> World. Indeed it is an old miſtake, a Branch of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Pride</hi> in Men, to attribute Victory and Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to their <hi>own Sword,</hi> their own Merit, Proweſs, and Gallantry, whereas they belong to a far different <hi>Cauſe.</hi> But <hi>Moſes</hi> hath long ſince determined againſt them in the Caſe of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Deut, 9.4.5. <hi>Speak not thou in thy heart, after that the Lord thy GOD hath caſt thine Enemies out before thee, ſaying, for my Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs hath the LORD brought me in to poſſeſs this Land, but for the Wickedneſs of theſe Nations the Lord doth drive them out; — Not for thy Righteouſneſs, or for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs of thine heart,</hi> (as he goes on) <hi>for thou art a ſtiff-necked and gain-ſaying People.</hi> Thus we ought not to impute our many and great Bleſſings, and particularly the late Wonderful <hi>Deliverance</hi> of Our Gracious KING, His only Royal Brother, and all His Moſt <hi>Loyal Subjects,</hi> out of the hands of thoſe <hi>Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirſty Men,</hi> to our own Righteouſneſs, but to their <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licions Wickedneſs;</hi> to GODS mere <hi>Mercy</hi> to us, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100576:11"/>Exemplary <hi>Juſtice</hi> upon them, for their ſtudied <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> Solemn <hi>Perjuries,</hi> Notorious <hi>Sacriledg,</hi> formed <hi>Conſpiracies,</hi> unwearied fowleſt <hi>Treaſons,</hi> and (which is the Spring of all their Motions) their damnable <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy</hi> in making a mock of all <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So many and ſuch weighty <hi>reaſons</hi> we have to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member</hi> HIM in the day of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Triumph</hi> (who <hi>remembred us when we were in trouble:</hi> and ſaved us ſo lately when we were upon the very brink of <hi>Ruin</hi>) and <hi>then</hi> eſpecially <hi>to beware leſt we forget the</hi> LORD.</p>
            <p>To cloſe up this Second general, 'tis a thouſand pities that <hi>fair weather ſhould do any harm;</hi> that when the <hi>Sun</hi> is moſt prodigal of his wealthy beams, and ſpends his richeft influence to maintain Natures Glory, he ſhould moſt tan her Beauty, and ſcorch her Hair; yet that it is ſo ſometimes every drought can witneſs; but it is not to be attributed to any blemiſh in the <hi>Sun,</hi> that bright Eye of the World, whoſe Rays are ever the ſame, apt to cheriſh and preſerve Life, but rather to the indiſpoſition of the <hi>matter</hi> before him, and thus it is no fault in the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs,</hi> that his heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beams do ruin and deſtroy us; that's the great imperfection of <hi>Men,</hi> who make their own Happineſs their Miſery, and turn their very <hi>Mercies</hi> into <hi>Sins,</hi> ſuch Fools and Brutes they are, that they will be ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er affrighted into a ſenſe of Religion by the Sword of GODS <hi>Judgments,</hi> and the <hi>black Rod</hi> of his Fury, then woed and courted to his ſervice by thoſe winning Arguments, his <hi>Golden Scepter</hi> of Love, and <hi>Staff</hi> of Comfort. Wherefore that we fall not afleep in ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity when the World <hi>ſmiles</hi> upon us, and all our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours are <hi>crowned</hi> with ſucceſs, I come</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:100576:11"/>3. In the Third and Laſt place, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ender you ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Directions,</hi> how we ſhould manage a full and <hi>proſperous Eſtate,</hi> how we may beſt reduce this uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>caution</hi> to practice. And</p>
            <p n="1">1. When thou thy ſelf art <hi>happy,</hi> don't trample upon, or inſult over them that are in <hi>miſery,</hi> but pitty them in ſome degree at leaſt, and if they ſuffer unjuſtly, do thy ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to relieve, and help them out; the <hi>Diſciples</hi> thought they asked our LORD a very ſubtile Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,—<hi>Did this man ſin, or his Parents, that he was lorn blind?</hi> but he tells them, <hi>neither,</hi> as they meant; he was not <hi>born Blind</hi> becauſe he or his Parents were <hi>greater ſinners</hi> than other men; but for this reaſon, that they (and others) if they were not <hi>blind, might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the glory of GOD</hi> in our Saviours working his cure, <hi>in the opening of his Eyes,</hi> and men are general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apt to make falſe conſtructions of GODS private <hi>Judgments</hi> in this Life: where they ſee them fall <hi>heavy</hi> they preſently cry, there dwells a more then ordinary <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>er,</hi> as if there were no after-reckoning, no <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to come; from whence they think themſelves obliged to help GOD to torment him, and fancy they <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Him ſervice,</hi> when they hate, ſcorn, kick, or bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et him, and <hi>heap more coals of fire upon his</hi> wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Head;</hi> ſuch <hi>fools</hi> are they, and <hi>ignorant</hi> of the myſterious Tracts, and hidden methods of the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine Providence,</hi> whoſe <hi>ways</hi> are all <hi>unſearchable,</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Paths paſt our finding out.</hi> How were his Wiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Rational Friends miſtaken in the caſe of poor <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ob?</hi> They concluded from his many and great <hi>ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> that he was the moſt <hi>wicked</hi> wretch, and noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ous <hi>Hypocrite</hi> under the cope of <hi>Heaven,</hi> when by GODS own Teſtimony, he was <hi>the moſt perfect, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ght man in all the Earth,</hi> and it ſtands upon ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſting record, that <hi>in all this</hi> (whether temptation
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100576:12"/>or trouble brought upon him by Men or Devils) <hi>in all this</hi> Job <hi>ſinned not, nor charged</hi> GOD <hi>fooliſhly;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let no Man <hi>judg before the time,</hi> conſidering there is <hi>another World,</hi> that will ſet all things <hi>right</hi> and <hi>ſtraight,</hi> which; his Folly thinks go ſomewhat <hi>oddly</hi> and <hi>awry</hi> in <hi>this, as we would that men ſhould do unto us, ſo let us do unto them,</hi> in their ſtraits, and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, their difficulties, and diſtreſſes, for if thou ſhouldſt deſpiſe or oppreſs thy <hi>poor Brother,</hi> when thou art <hi>rich,</hi> and <hi>full,</hi> it may be thou wouldſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs a <hi>JOB,</hi> a man of moſt admirable vertues, and higheſt <hi>Integrity;</hi> and thy <hi>weights</hi> and <hi>ballances</hi> are both <hi>falſe,</hi> if thou meaſureſt his <hi>ſins</hi> by his <hi>ſufferings.</hi> Suppoſe he be a very <hi>Judas,</hi> and known convicted <hi>Traytor;</hi> yet what is that to thee? <hi>Who made thee a Judge?</hi> It is enough that the <hi>Law</hi> takes publick <hi>Juſtice</hi> of him; all this while the <hi>Goſpel</hi> requires thee not to exclude him out of thy private <hi>Charity;</hi> beſides (ye know) it is very foul play to ſtrike a man when he is <hi>down,</hi> and baſeſt Cowardiſe to trample upon either a Living <hi>Dog,</hi> or a Dead <hi>Lyon.</hi> That's the Firſt,</p>
            <p n="2">2. When thou proſpereſt in the World, and liveſt according to thy Hearts deſire, then be ſure to let, <hi>Adverſity</hi> be the frequent object of thy retired thoughts and meditations. All things indeed go well with thee to day, <hi>but boaſt not thy ſelf</hi> (ſays <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>of to morrow, for thou knoweſt not what a Day may bring forth, Quamobrem omnes cùm res ſecundae ſunt maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè, tum maximè meditari ſecum oportet, quo pacte advorſam aerumnam ferant, pericla, damna, exilia, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith the comedian; willing us not to be ſecure in our <hi>proſperity,</hi> but then learn to expect and bear any evil tidings, or adverſe fortune. Holy <hi>Job</hi> (now in his Wealth and Grandeur) took an excellent courſe for this, and well worthy all our imitation, when his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100576:12"/>
               <hi>Children had been long Feaſting together by turns from houſe to houſe,</hi> the good old Man <hi>went and Offered burnt Offerings according to the Number of them all; For it may be</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>my Sons have Sinned, and Curſed GOD in their Hearts.</hi> Though he knew of nothing but a Lawful Recreation, yet, <hi>it may be,</hi> for fear of the worſt, he went to his <hi>Devotions,</hi> and offered <hi>Sacrifice;</hi> as knowing there would be no hurt in <hi>that</hi> however, but that it might prevent ſome unſeen <hi>Miſchief.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed common <hi>Prudence</hi> may inſtruct us all to look for Miſchances, and expect <hi>Troubles</hi> before they come, that when they do come, we may be upon our <hi>Guard</hi> to receive them. <hi>After Wit</hi> is for none but <hi>Fools</hi> to brag of; a <hi>Wiſer</hi> Man takes his Meaſures by looking <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as well <hi>before,</hi> as <hi>behind</hi> him, and ſo is able in time to take out the Sting of an <hi>Evil</hi> before it can reach him. Then, think of <hi>Loſſes,</hi> when you <hi>thrive</hi> the moſt, of <hi>Wars</hi> in <hi>Peace,</hi> of <hi>VVant</hi> in <hi>Plenty,</hi> of <hi>Grief</hi> in <hi>Joy,</hi> of <hi>Sickneſs</hi> in <hi>Health,</hi> and of <hi>Death</hi> it ſelf in the midſt of <hi>Life,</hi> and then no <hi>Change</hi> of things can ſurprize or harm you, but (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> obſerves) <hi>all things ſhall work together for good to them that love GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Uſe thine abundance with all <hi>Moderation,</hi> abuſe it not to gratifie thy craving <hi>Luſts,</hi> and Inſatiable <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</hi> for they are abſurd and <hi>unreaſonable men,</hi> who think they do not truly rejoyce in GODS <hi>Bleſſings,</hi> runleſs they may Sacrifice them by <hi>whole-ſale</hi> to their greedy <hi>Appetites;</hi> who madly fancy they cannot be happy, if their <hi>deſires</hi> be held to any Stint or Bounds. hence comes all their exceſs in Eating and Drinking, and other Lawful Pleaſures: They think to <hi>take their fill</hi> of Enjoyment, and glut themſelves with the Marrow and Quinteſſence of all <hi>Good things,</hi> and ſo miſtake the <hi>Quantity</hi> for the <hi>Quality;</hi> whereas
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100576:13"/>in truth, all Earthly <hi>Pleaſure</hi> Commends it ſelf in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, than as it is more <hi>ſeldom-uſed.</hi> Therefore, if GOD hath given thee Increaſe of <hi>Corn</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> uſe them with all <hi>Caution,</hi> and <hi>Sobriety.</hi> Ear not too greedily of the <hi>Corn:</hi> For a full <hi>Belly</hi> is moſt unfit for <hi>Devotion</hi> and <hi>Contemplation;</hi> beſides that it breeds ill Humours, and endangers <hi>Health.</hi> And drink not too freely of the <hi>Wine;</hi> for though it be good and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and <hi>move it ſelf aright,</hi> yet too much thereof will <hi>Intoxicate;</hi> it will drown thy Reaſon and <hi>Parts,</hi> enervate all thy Faculties, and <hi>Powers,</hi> and make thee <hi>forget,</hi> or <hi>deny the Lord thy GOD,</hi> or take his <hi>Holy Name in Vain.</hi> And for all other lawful Diverſions take that one Counſel of the Wiſe, experienced <hi>King, Prov.</hi> 25. <hi>Haſt thou found Honey? Eat ſo much thereof as is ſufficient for thee</hi> (and no more) <hi>leſt thou be filled therewith, and womit it up again.</hi> There's no other way but that, to prevent a <hi>Surfeit,</hi> whether in Body or Mind. But you'l ſay perhaps, what muſt I them do with mine <hi>Abundance?</hi> For after this rate of <hi>Dieting</hi> my ſelf, I ſhall never live to <hi>ſpend</hi> it. Why, yes; there is another, a <hi>more excellent way</hi> to be rid of the overplus to better advantage; and that ſhall be my</p>
            <p n="4">4. Direction. Be <hi>Hoſpitable, Charitable,</hi> and free to Communicate what thou canſt well ſpare, to Relieve the <hi>Wants</hi> and Supply the <hi>Neceſſities</hi> of others. For GOD hath made thee <hi>Rich</hi> on purpoſe to be their <hi>Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi> and <hi>Almoner,</hi> and (as little as ſome Men heed it) will one day expect a good <hi>Accompt</hi> of that <hi>Steward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</hi> It is the <hi>Miſers</hi> great miſtake to think at his Choice and Liberty, and purely in his own Power, whether he will expend his Superfluities in <hi>good works,</hi> or no; for the Law of <hi>Juſtice</hi> requires, it of him, although, from the mannor, end, and ſome other circumſtances, we commonly call it <hi>Charity.</hi> That <hi>Fool</hi> in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100576:13"/>needed not to have put himſelf to ſo much trouble and Charge in <hi>building his Barus bigger,</hi> to lodg his plentiful Crop; there was Barn-room enough in the World, if he would have ſeen it; for, as St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> obſerves, <hi>the Bellies of the Poor are GODS Granary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If therefore thou haſt any <hi>Bread to ſpare, caſt it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Waters</hi> (as <hi>Solomon</hi> adviſeth that is, venture it among the Multitude, rather then fail) though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo troubleſome and unworthy, <hi>and thou ſhalt find it again after many days;</hi> for however Men may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful, yet GOD <hi>is not unrighteous to forget any work or labour of Love. St.</hi> Paul bids us <hi>Charge them that are Rich in this World, that they be Rich in good Works, ready to diſtribute, willing to Communicate.</hi> And again, that, as they have Ability, and <hi>Opportunity, they do good unto all Men, eſpecially to them who are of the Houſehold of Faith;</hi> he means chiefly thoſe, that <hi>Miniſter at the Altar,</hi> and daily <hi>watch over your Souls. For this is pure Religion, and undefiled before</hi> GOD, whereby a Man ſhall not only preſerve himſelf Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and impregnable to all the Temptations of a full and <hi>proſperous Eſtate,</hi> but alſo <hi>make himſelf Friends of the</hi> Mammon <hi>of unrighteouſneſs, who</hi> when he faileth here, <hi>may receive him into thoſe everlaſting Habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of GOD and his Son JESUS CHRIST, and all his Holy <hi>Saints</hi> and Elect <hi>Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5ly. and laſtly, For <hi>yet thou lackeſt one thing,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which all other <hi>directions</hi> will prove Vain and Uſeleſs; and that is this: Reſolve, with Penitent <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, to give thy ſelf unto Prayer;</hi> To implore the <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> of GODS Holy Spirit day by day, whoſe proper Work and Office it is to <hi>Sanctifie</hi> all Conditions of Life to us: As well to keep us <hi>down</hi> when we begin to be <hi>Elevated</hi> into Pride, as to buoy our Spirits up, and be our <hi>Comforter</hi> in extream Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:100576:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Prayer</hi> is that powerful Engine whereby <hi>the Kingdom of Heaven ſuffereth Violence, and the Violent take it by Force:</hi> whereby Mortal Men <hi>wreſtle with the</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal GOD, and <hi>will not let him go till he hath bleſſed them.</hi> That Sedulous <hi>Importunity</hi> which once extorted <hi>Juſtice</hi> from an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt Judge,</hi> muſt needs be ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent for <hi>Mercy</hi> with the Righteous <hi>Judge of all the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I had almoſt ſaid that (under GOD) the KING ows his late never-to-be-forgotten <hi>Preſervation,</hi> in a great Meaſure, to the <hi>Prayers</hi> of the Church offered up daily on his behalf; that GOD would ſave him from all his undeſerved <hi>Enemies,</hi> whoſe <hi>tender Mercies are Cruel,</hi> and their very <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Preachments are of Curſing and Lies,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks.</p>
            <p>I'm ſure his Martyr'd <hi>Father,</hi> of ever Bleſſed <hi>Memory</hi> (whoſe Innocent blood perhaps GOD is <hi>making</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial <hi>Inquiſition for</hi> at this time) hath left us an uſeful <hi>Note</hi> to this purpoſe, amongſt other his Sacred Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, which I ſhall crave leave to Read you in his own <hi>Royal</hi> Words.</p>
            <p>One of the Greateſt Faults ſome Men found with the Common-Prayer-Book, I believe, <hi>(faith that Great, Good and Juſt Man)</hi> was this: That it taught them to <hi>Pray</hi> ſo oft for me; to which Petitions they had not Loyalty enough to ſay AMEN, nor yet Charity enough to forbear Reproaches, and even <hi>Curſings</hi> of me, in their own Forms, inſtead of <hi>Praying</hi> for me. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>ch.</hi> 16.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:100576:14"/>
            <p>The <hi>Text</hi> is ſo very plain that it needs no <hi>comment,</hi> (were I worthy to make it) and therefore ſo I ſhall leave it. Mean while (to return to may own <hi>Argument,</hi> from this <hi>Digreſſion,</hi> I could not fairly avoid) <hi>Who art thou O Man,</hi> who upon any ſcore, canſt truſt to thine own <hi>ſtrength?</hi> It will betray, and fail thee; it is no better then a <hi>broken Reed,</hi> for though <hi>the Spirit</hi> may be ſometimes <hi>willing:</hi> though thy <hi>Judgment</hi> be convinced, and thy <hi>Will</hi> alſo made a <hi>Proſelyte</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve upon this, or that <hi>good work,</hi> yet it is often left undone, in regard <hi>the Fleſh is always weak.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>—Video meliora probóque.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Deteriora ſequor</hi>— is the <hi>natural</hi> Mans true Motto; it is all he can juſtly pretend to, to commend Vertue in the <hi>notion,</hi> but condemn it ſtill in his own <hi>Practice;</hi> and I muſt obſerve it to you for a great <hi>Truth</hi> (however ſome may ſeem to Preach quite the contrary <hi>Doctrine,</hi> or at leaſt, not to preſs <hi>this</hi> ſo often, nor ſo earneſtly as they ſhould) <hi>That, Mens truſting to their own natural Powers, and not regarding, nor du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly asking GODS ſpecial Grace and help,</hi> (as if they meant to bid deſpite to his Holy Spirit) <hi>is one main, if not the only reaſon of their perſiſting in their old im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties,</hi> and particularly, <hi>of their abuſing and forfeiting their temporal bleſſings, and hazarding their hopes alſo of Eternal Life.</hi> For thus ſaith the Lord GOD, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.5. <hi>Curſed be the Man that putteth his truſt in Man, or maketh Fleſh his Arm!</hi> Be it the <hi>Man</hi> himſelf, or any other mere <hi>Man,</hi> all's a caſe; he is ſtill <hi>accurſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore let no Man living <hi>boaſt of his infirmities,</hi> nor <hi>Glory</hi> in his ſhame; let us not preſume upon our own <hi>Strength</hi> (or <hi>Weakneſs</hi> rather) nor magnifie the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of <hi>Nature</hi> in derogation to the <hi>Grace</hi> of GOD, by which alone we muſt be <hi>ſaved;</hi> but rather let us with Holy <hi>David</hi> (as in utmoſt duty bound) <hi>Make
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100576:15"/>the LORD our only confidence, the moſt High GOD the Rock of our Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as the Eternal <hi>Son of GOD</hi> our <hi>Saviour</hi> hath ſolemnly, and freely promiſed us, that <hi>whatſoever we ſhall ask the Father in</hi> HIS NAME, <hi>He will give it us:</hi> and particularly this ineſtimable and neceſſary Gift of his Holy SPIRIT, recorded for our great and endleſs comfort, St. <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13. and St. <hi>John</hi> 15.16. (which by the way, is the true reaſon that all our Publick <hi>Prayers</hi> run in that <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Style,</hi> and are ſhut up, and bidden GOD ſpeed for the ſake and <hi>merits</hi> of JESUS CHRIST OUR LORD.)</p>
            <p>Let us humbly, heartily, and inceſſantly mention the Holy Name of JESUS before the Throne of the Eternal TRINITY; that GOD would vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe his Holy SPIRIT to dwell in all our <hi>Hearts,</hi> to <hi>help our Infirmities,</hi> and <hi>lead us into all Truth,</hi> to <hi>ſubdue</hi> our natural <hi>Pride,</hi> and <hi>ſanctifie</hi> all our <hi>Mercies</hi> Spiritual and Temporal; that we may <hi>uſe</hi> this <hi>World,</hi> and not <hi>abuſe</hi> it, and ever be careful, leſt in the midſt of the many and great <hi>Bleſſings</hi> we now enjoy, we ſhould <hi>forget the</hi> LORD, the Author of them all; that ſo he may not be provoked to <hi>forget,</hi> but may in much mercy <hi>remember</hi> us, in <hi>that day when he maketh up his Jewels,</hi> and may <hi>bind up our Souls in the bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of Life;</hi> which GOD grant for the ſame JESUS ſake, our only Redeemer, to whom with the FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER and the Holy GHOST, <hi>Three</hi> Perſons, and <hi>One</hi> GOD, be all the Power and Glory, Praiſe and Thankſgiving, now and for ever more, AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:100576:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
